What you doing?
Que fais—tu ?
You said clean up. I'm cleaning up, heh.
Tu as dit de ranger. Je range.
You can't just throw everything in the closet.
Tu jettes tout dans le placard ?
You can tell me what to do or you can tell me how to do it...
Tu ne peux pas me donner des ordres.
...but you can't do both. This isn't sex.
On n'est pas en train de coucher ensemble.
Well, what if someone looks in there?
Et si quelqu'un regarde ?
They're coming over for dinner, no one will look in the closet.
Ils viennent pour dîner. Personne ne viendra la.
You don't know that. What if someone's looking for the bathroom?
Tu l'ignores.
It could work out.
Possible.
For all we know, there's a toilet in there somewhere.
Il y a des toilettes quelque part dans le tas.
Fine. After tonight, we need to get a handle on this mess.
Après ce soir, nous devons ranger ce bazar.
We should show the closet to Sheldon.
On devrait le montrer à Sheldon.
Why?
Pourquoi ?
Ha. Are you kidding? He's like a savant at organizing.
C‘est un savant dans l‘art du rangement.
Everything in his apartment has a label on it...
Ses objets portent des étiquettes,
...including his label maker, which has a label that says "label maker."
même son étiqueteur porte une étiquette ”étiqueteur".
If you look really close at that label-maker label, you'll see a label that says "label."
Si tu regardes de plus près,
No, he's our guest. We can't ask him to straighten our closet.
Il est notre invité.
No, we wouldn't ask him.
On ne lui demandera pas.
We'd just show him the closet and let the goblins in his head take it from there.
On lui montre le placard et on laisse les gobelins dans sa tête s'activer.
HOWARD: Hey, guys, come on in.
Entrez.
AMY: Hi. -Ooh, it smells good.
- Bonsoir. - Ça sent bon.
Thanks. Sheldon, I know tonight's the night you eat Thai food.
Merci. Sheldon, je sais que ce soir tu manges thaï,
I went to the Asian market, got the ingredients, made it from scratch.
alors j'ai cuisiné thaï de A a Z.
Oh, you shouldn't have.
Tu n'aurais pas dû.
It was my pleasure.
C'était un plaisir.
No, you really shouldn't have.
Non. Tu n'aurais vraiment pas dû.
I brought my own.
J'ai apporté mon repas.
You stopped and got him takeout?
Tu l'as déposé au restaurant ?
I had no choice. He kept kicking the back of my seat.
Pas le choix. Il donnait des coups dans mon siège.
Sheldon, I've been cooking all day.
J'ai cuisiné toute lajournée.
Well, now don't you feel silly?
Tu te sens idiote, non ?
Show him the closet.
Montre—lui le placard.
These spring rolls are amazing. Good job, Bernadette.
Ces rouleaux de printemps sont délicieux.
That's the takeout that Sheldon brought.
C‘est le plat à emporter de Sheldon.
I'm sure they wouldn't have tasted nearly as good if I hadn't tried your food first.
Ils n'auraient pas été aussi bons si je n‘avais pas goûté les tiens.
Howard, did you want your clothes arranged seasonally or by color?
Tu veux un rangement par saison ou par couleur ?
-Color's fine. -Wrong, they'll be arranged seasonally.
- Couleur. - Faux. Par saison.
Aren't you gonna spend a little time with Amy?
Tu ne veux pas passer du temps avec Amy ?
Oh, it's okay, I'm used to it.
Ca va. J'ai l‘habitude.
The other day at Whole Foods, he spent an hour optimizing the cheese aisle.
L‘autre jour, à l'épicerie, il a rangé leur allée de fromages.
And some thanks I got.
Quels remerciements!
The assistant manager chased me out with an artisanal salami.
Leur assistant m‘a poursuivi avec du salami.
His quirks just make you love him more.
Son excentricité nous force a l'aimer.
Someone please agree with me.
Acquiescez.
Come on. It's getting late. Time to go.
Sheldon, viens. Il est tard.
Oh! Five more minutes.
Encore cinq minutes.
That's what you said five minutes ago.
Tu as dit ça il y a cinq minutes.
Amy and Penny are already in the car, move it.
Amy et Penny sont dans la voiture.
How come I never get to do anything I wanna do?
Pourquoi je ne peux jamais faire ce que je veux ?
If he really wants to stay and finish, I can give him a ride home.
S'il veut vraiment rester, je le ramènerai.
Please, Leonard. He said it's okay.
S'il te plaît, Leonard. Il est d‘accord.
Sheldon, it's-- Wait, I can go home without you? Bye.
C'est... Je peux rentrer sans toi.
Howard, l have a few questions.
J'ai quelques questions.
I found three bowling pins.
J'ai trouvé trois quilles de bowling.
Now, do you juggle these or are you missing seven?
Tu jongles avec ou tu en as perdu sept ?
-Juggle. -You health nuts kill me.
- Je jongle. - Ta santé mentale me tue.
Oh, my God, it's beautiful!
C‘est splendide!
And look, you found thejuggling pins I hid.
Et tu as trouvé ces quilles que je cachais.
Now, a couple more items.
Encore d'autres objets.
Howard, I found this letter from your dad in a box.
J'ai trouvé une lettre de ton père.
-Based on content, it could either be filed-- -Wait, you opened this?
- D'après son contenu, je… - Tu l'as ouverte ?
I had to find out if it's personal correspondence or memorabilia.
Pour savoir si c'était personnel ou des souvenirs.
-Based on the content-- -I couldn't be less interested.
- D'après le… - Ca ne m‘intéresse pas.
Now, come on, I'll take you home.
Viens. Je te ramène chez toi.
-Don't you want to know what's in it? -lfl did, I would've opened it years ago.
- Tu ne veux pas savoir ? - J'aurais pu l'ouvrir avant.
The closet looks great. Let's get out of here.
Le placard est parfait. Sortons de la.
Can I bring this box of extra shirt buttons to sort on the ride?
Je peux apporter cette boite de boutons pour les trier en route ?
-Do whatever you want. -Thanks.
- Si tu veux. - Merci.
Great party.
Super fête.
When I first met Howard, he'd pull his scrotum out of his shorts and say:
La première fois, il a soulevé son scrotum en disant:
"Oh! I sat in gum."
”J‘ai du chewing-gum au derrière."
What is your point?
Et alors ?
It's kind of weird how grown up he is now. Happily married, throwing dinner parties.
Etrange. Maintenant, c‘est un homme marié qui organise des soirées.
Really? You couldn'tjust say that? You had to tell the scrotum story?
Et tu étais obligé de me parler de son scrotum ?
LEONARD: Trying to paint a picture.
C'était pour illustrer mes propos.
It was a nice change of pace, not eating takeout around a coffee table.
C'était chouette de ne pas manger comme d‘habitude.
We could throw a dinner party too. Maybe even ask everyone to get dressed up.
On devrait organiser une soirée. Avec des tenues.
Sure. Just, when you say "dressed up," you mean nice clothes, right?
Quand tu parles de tenues, tu parles de jolis habits ?
Not like capes and tights and crap.
Pas de cape, de collants et tout.
Yeah.
- Oui. Mais... - Non.
-Howie, you okay? -Yeah, I just couldn't sleep.
- Ça va ? - Je n'arrivais pas a dormir.
I told you you shouldn't have espresso after dinner.
Tu ne devrais pas boire de café le soir.
I know the little cups make you feel big, but it's not worth it.
Je sais que tu te sens plus fort mais ce n‘est pas la peine.
It's this stupid letter.
C‘est cette lettre.
-Did you read it? -No.
- Tu l'as lue ? - Non.
-You must be curious. -Of course I'm curious.
- Tu dois être curieux. - Bien sûr.
I haven't seen the man since I was a little kid.
Je n'ai pas revu cet homme depuis mon enfance.
And a letter shows up on my 18th birthday.
Et il envoie une lettre pour mes 18 ans ?
What's that about?
A quel sujet ?
Then why don't you read it?
Tu n'as qu'à la lire.
Maybe he apologizes or explains why he left.
Peut-être qu'il s'excuse ou qu'il s‘explique.
He abandoned me and my mother.
Il nous a abandonnés.
Why does he deserve a chance to explain anything?
Pourquoi mériterait-il une chance de s‘expliquer ?
I get that.
Je comprends.
So, what do you wanna do with it?
Que veux-tu en faire ?
Something I should've done a long time ago.
Ce que j'aurais dû faire il y a longtemps.
Really? Are you sure?
Vraiment ? Tu es sérieux ?
Yep.
Oui.
Feel better?
Ça va mieux ?
Great.
Super.
Neither one of us is tall enough to reach that.
Aucun de nous n‘est assez grand pour l'atteindre.
I can't believe he set it on fire.
llyamis lefeu ?
Yeah, just seeing that letter really freaked him out.
Voir cette lettre, ça l‘a rendu triste.
And he was already having a tough day. He accidentally wore my pants to work.
Déjà qu'il était mal car il a porté mon pantalon au travail.
I don't know why he was upset. They were bigger on him than me.
Je ne comprends pas. Il était trop grand pour lui.
I'm really curious what's in that letter.
J'aurais aimé lire cette lettre.
Me too, but I guess now we'll never know.
Moi aussi. Nous ne saurons jamais.
You said Sheldon read it. Why not ask him?
Sheldon l‘a lue. Demande-lui.
I can't do that. What kind of wife would I be ifl didn't respect my husband's privacy?
Non. Quelle femme je serais si je ne respectais pas son intimité ?
What ifl ask and you happen to be in the room?
Si je lui demande et que tu es dans la pièce ?
-That works. -Okay.
- Ça marche. - Parfait.
It's like cleaning out the entire building's belly button.
C‘est comme nettoyer le nombril de tous les voisins.
-Hey, Sheldon. SHELDON: Oh, hello.
- Salut. - Bonjour.
What can I do for you ladies?
Que voulez-vous ?
-You have something we want. -Oh, dear.
- Quelque chose que tu as. - Bon sang.
My mother warned me this is what happens to pretty boys in the big city.
Ma mère m‘avait averti de ce qui arrivait aux gentils garcons.
No, we just want information.
Non. Nous voulons des informations.
We heard you read the letter from Howard's father.
Tu as lu la lettre du père d‘Howard.
-I did. -What did it say?
- Oui. - Que disait-elie ?
I can't tell you that.
Je ne peux rien dire.
I'm bound by closet organizer-organizee confidentiality.
Je suis tenu parla clause de confidentialité.
Sheldon, that's not a real thing.
Ce n‘est pas une régie.
Neither is the rule that you have to hold your girlfriend's hand at the movies.
Et tenir la main de sa petite amie, c'en est une ?
But that doesn't stop you from pawing at me...
Ça ne t‘a pas empêchée de me tripoter
...like you're a bear and I'm a trash can full of sweets.
comme si tu étais un ours et moi une poubelle remplie de miel.
Why do you even care? Just tell us what it says.
On s'en moque. bis—nous.
Control over the information contained in that letter belongs to Howard.
Le contrôle des informations de la lettre revient a Howard.
By happenstance, I came to know it.
Par hasard, je l'ai lue.
That doesn't give me the right to disseminate it freely.
Cela ne me donne pas le droit de Ia disséminer.
The letter was found in Bernadette's closet. Doesn't that count for something?
La lettre était dans le placard de Bernadette. Alors ?
Are you pointing out that California is a community-property state...
lnsinues-tu que la Californie est un Etat de communauté des biens
...and since Howard and Bernadette are married, intellectual property in the letter...
et que, comme ils sont mariés, la propriété de la lettre
...is jointly owned by the two spouses?
revient aux deux époux ?
Yeah, obviously.
Oui, évidemment.
Well played.
Bien joué.
Sometimes I don't give you enough credit, Penny.
Je ne t‘accorde pas assez de crédit.
Dude, you made the right choice coming to me for help with this party.
Tu as fait le bon choix en me demandant mon aide.
Actually, all I did was invite you.
Je t‘avais juste invité.
Well, put your mind at ease.
Détends-toi.
I'm here to make sure your dinner party kicks Howard's dinner party's ass.
Je vais faire en sorte que ce diner écrase la soirée d‘Howard.
Now, the first thing we need is a theme.
Pour commencer, il nous faut un théme.
I'm thinking, ah, turn-of-the-century Moulin Rouge.
J'ai pensé au Moulin Rouge du début du siècle.
I'm thinking you need a testosterone patch.
Je pense que tu as besoin d'un patch de testostérone.
Penny and I just wanna do something low-key.
On veut quelque chose de sobre.
You know, cocktails, lightjazz music, hors d'oeuvres.
Cocktails, jazz, hors d‘œuvres.
So your theme is "I saw a rerun of Mad Men and bought crab puffs from Trader Joe's"?
Ton thème est : "Rediffusion de Mad Men et choux au crabe" ?
I'd hate to miss that. Ahem.
Je ne veux pas rater ça.
Hey, where have you been?
Où étais-tu ?
Oh, Leonard.
Oh, Leonard.
If I was prone to sarcasm...
Si j‘étais enclin aux sarcasmes,
...l'd say I was pulling off a major heist at the Museum of Laundry Baskets.
je dirais que j'ai fait un casse au Musée dela Machine a laver.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, 10.
Un, deux, trois, quatre, cinq, six, sept, huit, neuf, 10.
I meant, golly, Sheldon, you've been gone a long time.
Tu as été long.
Oh, well, I was waylaid by Penny, Bernadette and Amy.
J'ai été retenu par Penny, Bernadette et Amy.
They made me reveal confidential information about Howard's father.
Elles m‘ont fait parler au sujet de la lettre.
-What information? -I can't tell you that.
- Elle dit quoi ? -Je ne peux rien dire.
I'm bound by closet organizer-organizee confidentiality.
Je suis tenu parla clause de confidentialité.
Come on, we won't tell anyone.
Nous ne dirons rien.
Sorry, badgering me won't work. What you should have said is:
Ça ne marche pas. Tu aurais plutôt du dire:
"It's pointless to keep this a secret. Penny will tell."
"Peu importe. Penny nous racontera."
-Fine, then that. -All right, I'll tell you.
- Alors, ça. - D‘accord. Je vous raconte.
My goodness, everyone's on their game today.
Bonté divine, tout le monde fait le tapin aujourd'hui.
This is really fun.
C‘est trés sympa.
Yeah, it's nice to get dressed up once in awhile.
C‘est chouette d‘être bien habillé.
And the hors d'oeuvres are delightful.
- Le buffet est délicieux. - La compagnie aussi.
My shirt is itchy, and lwish l were dead.
Ca me gratte. Je voudrais être mort.
Hey, everybody, before Howard gets here, let's all just agree...
Avant qu'Howard arrive, n‘oubliez pas de ne pas
-...to not bring up the letter. -Of course.
- parler de la lettre. - Oui.
PENNY: Sure. AMY: Absolutely.
- Absolument.
If I say yes, can we turn off that Latin orgy music?
Si je dis "oui", je peux éteindre ce bruit ?
It's ridiculous that we still have to walk up all these flights of stairs.
C‘est ridicule de devoir encore monter les escaliers.
-Yeah, try doing it in heels. -I am.
- Essaie de le faire en talons. - C‘est le cas.
Wait. There's something I have to tell you.
Attends. Je dois te parler.
-What? -I know what was in your dad's letter.
- Quoi ? - Je connais le contenu de la lettre.
Sheldon, I swear to God I'm gonna kill you!
Sheldon, je jure que je vais te tuer!
Hey!
Hé!
I made him tell us.
Nous lui avons demandé.
"Us"? Who else knows?
Nous ? Qui d‘autre le sait ?
-I know. -Me too.
- Je sais. - Moi.
Same here.
Ici aussi.
Shame on all of you.
Honte à vous.
You know too.
Tu sais aussi.
Couldn't leave him with one friend, could you?
Tu ne pouvais pas lui laisser un ami ?
So everybody knows what's in that letter except for me?
Tout le monde sait sauf moi ?
Yes, it's six against one. Stand down, sir.
C‘est six contre un. Capitulez, monsieur.
How could you do this?
Comment as-tu osé ?
I'm sorry.
Je suis désolée.
-If you want, we could tell you. -I don't want to know.
- On peut te le dire. - Je ne veux pas savoir.
I do, but....
Si, mais…
I gotta go.
Je préfère partir.
Used me as a human shield?
Tu m'as utilisée comme un bouclier humain ?
l panicked.
J'ai paniqué.
He looked taller than usual.
Il avait l‘air plus grand que d‘habitude.
BERNADETTE: Howard?
Howard ?
In here.
Ici.
Sorry.
Désolée.
lshould've left it alone.
Je n'aurais pas dû.
It's okay. I'm sorry I ran off like that.
Ça va.
What are you looking at?
Que regardes-tu ?
Pictures of my dad and me when l was a kid.
Des photos de mon père et moi.
-That's nice. -I gotta tell you...
C‘est chouette.
...as angry as I am at Sheldon for blabbing...
Même si je suis en colère contre Sheldon,
...he did a hell of ajob organizing this closet.
il a fait du sacré travail en rangeant le placard.
Look at this.
Regarde.
"Photos of Wolowitz Family Before Father Left Forever."
"Photo de famille avant le départ du père pour toujours."
Neither race was happy to see me with those.
Personne n‘était content de me voir avec ça.
Think you can take a break?
Tu fais une pause ?
-Why? -Got a little surprise for you.
- Pourquoi ? - J'ai une surprise pour toi.
Come on.
Viens.
Oh, honey...
Chérie,
...I am in no mood to have sex tonight.
je ne suis pas d'humeur a avoir des relations sexuelles.
I mean, I'll lay there if you absolutely have to have it, but--
Je veux bien m'allonger si tu veux absolument...
What are you guys doing here?
Que faites-vous la ?
You weren't sure whether you wanted to know what was in your dad's letter...
NOUS ne SﬂVOHS pas
...so we came up with kind of a cool solution.
alors nous avons trouvé une solution.
Oh, yeah? What's that?
Ah, oui ?
It's simple, really.
C‘est simple.
It occurred to me that knowing and not knowing...
A mes yeux, l'hésitation peut subsister
...can be achieved by creating a macroscopic example of quantum superposition...
en créant un exemple macroscopique de superpositions quantiques
...the principle that a physical system exists partially in all its possible states at once.
sur le principe qu'elle existe partiellement dans les énoncés.
We were all thinking it, really.
Nous le pensons tous.
It was kind of the elephant in the room, so....
C‘est notre porte—parole.
Anyway, um, I realized if we each present you...
Si chacun d‘entre nous te raconte
...with an account of what your father wrote to you...
une version de la lettre de ton pére
...only one of which is true, and we don't tell you which one it is...
et qu‘une seule est la vraie, sans que tu ne saches laquelle,
...you will forever be in a state of epistemic ambivalence.
tu resteras toujours dans un état d‘ambivalence épistémique.
Yeah, and I said if it wasn't epistemic, we might as well not do it.
Si ce n‘était pas épistémique, ce ne serait pas nécessaire.
Sit down, honey.
Assieds-toi.
-Raj, you're up. -Okay, um, ahem.
- Raj, a toi. - D‘accord.
It was a card for your 18th birthday.
C‘était une carte pour ton 18e anniversaire.
Inside it said, "Happy birthday, Howard. I love you. Dad."
Il était écrit : ”Joyeux anniversaire. Je t‘aime. Papa."
Oh, and it was a "Far Side" card...
C‘était une carte "Far Side",
...the one where the frog has its tongue stuck to the underside of an airplane.
celle avec la grenouille qui a sa langue collée sous un avion.
Thinks it's a fly.
Elie croit que c‘est une mouche.
Silly frog. So funny.
Stupide grenouille. Trop drôle.
Sheldon?
Sheldon ?
It was a map...
C‘était une carte
...leading to the lost treasure of famous pirate "One-Eyed Willy."
qui mène au trésor perdu du célèbre pirate Willy Ie Borgne.
Nice try. That's the plot for Goonies.
Bien essayé. C‘est l'intrigue des Goonies.
-Told you. -Don't.
- Je te l‘avais dit. - Tais-toi.
Amy?
Amy ?
You didn't know it...
Tu l‘ignorais,
...but your father was in the auditorium at your high school graduation...
mais ton père était présent lors dela remise des diplômes,
...and he cried because he was so proud of you.
et il a pleuré car il était fier de toi.
Really?
Vraiment ?
Or that's complete poppycock which Amy made up. It still could be the map.
Des sornettes qu‘Amy a inventées. La carte, c‘est possible.
Penny?
Penny ?
It was a letter explaining that your dad wasn't who he said he was.
C‘était une lettre expliquant que ton pére menait une double vie.
Eventually his other life caught up to him...
Son autre vie a pris le dessus
...and the only way to keep you and your mom safe was to leave.
et il a dû partir pour vous protéger.
I would like to change mine.
Je veux changer ma version.
The pirate's name was Peg-Leg Antoine.
Le pirate s‘appelle Antoine Jambe de bois.
Now it's completely different from Goonies.
Complètement différent des Goonies.
-No, it's not. -Don't.
- Non. - Tais-toi.
Okay, my tu rn.
A mon tour.
Your dad wrote about how family is the most important thing...
Il a écrit que la famille compte plus que tout
...and that you should never throw it away like he did.
et qu'il n'aurait pas dû vous abandonner.
Bernadette?
Bernadette ?
In the envelope was a picture of your dad holding you the day you were born.
Il y avait une photo de ton père et toi a ta naissance.
On the back he wrote, "Howard, my son, my greatest gift."
Derrière, il y avait écrit : ”Howard, mon fils, mon cadeau."
You okay?
Çava?
Yeah.
Oui.
I'm terrific.
Je vais très bien.
So...?
Alors ?
Which one do you think it is...
Laquelle est la bonne ?
Actually, I don't wanna know.
Je ne veux pas le savoir.
I want all of them to be true.
J'aimerais qu‘elles soient toutes vraies.
Well, one of them is.
L‘une d‘elles l'est.
That's pretty cool.
C‘est chouette.
Thank you, guys.
Merci.
Hey, it's still early. Why don't we go back and have that party?
Il est encore tôt. Si on retournait a la soirée ?
-Yeah. -Okay.
- Oui. - D‘accord.
Yeah, surprisingly...
Etonnamment,
...the letter from your father wasn't the most interesting thing in the closet.
cette lettre n‘était pas la chose la plus intéressante dans le placard.
Bernadette's diary has some saucy passages.
Le journal de Bernadette contient des passages osés.
-Sheldon, don't you dare. -Nothing to worry about.
- Tu n'as pas osé. - Ne t'inquiète pas.
Your secret's safe with me.
Tes secrets sont en sécurité.
That's more like it.
J‘espère.
Although copyright law would allow me to quote snippets in the context of a review.
La propriété intellectuelle m'autorise àla citer dans une revue.
I'm glad you're feeling better.
Je suis contente que ça aille.
But if I'd known we were gonna be dancing, I would've wore my flats.
Si j‘avais su que nous allions danser, j'aurais mis mes mocassins.
-Well, this turned out pretty well, huh? -Yeah, I think so.
- Ça se passe plutôt bien ? - Je trouve.
I agree. That is, if you've never been to or heard of a party before.
Je suis d‘accord. Si vous n‘êtes jamais allés à une fête avant.
If you'd let me pierce your brain with a hot needle in the right place...
Si je te traverse le cerveau avec une aiguille,
...you'd be happy all the time.
tu seras tout le temps heureux.
Penny, l have a couple of questions about your closet.
Penny, j'ai des questions sur ton placard.
Is there any reason you're keeping this dead goldfish?
Il y a une raison pour que tu gardes ce poisson rouge mort ?
Damn, I forgot to feed him.
Bon sang. J'ai oublié de le nourrir.
And thatl had him.
Et que je l'avais.
Well, now, did you also have a dog?
As-tu eu un chien ?
Because I found what appears to be a battery-operated chew toy--
Carj'ai trouvé ce qui pourrait être un jouet vibrant...
Party's over! Party's over!
La fête est terminée !
[English - us - an]
[French]